Finding aid to the Mina Kirstein Curtiss Papers CA.MS.00047
Smith College Archives
Mina Kirstein Curtiss Papers
1915-1983
1918-1945
Smith College Archives
Curtiss, Mina Kirstein, 1896-
CA.MS.00047
2.708 linear feet (4 containers)
Class of 1918, Professor of English, author. Collection contains biographical material, correspondence, examinations, lectures, publications, and student papers.
Biographical / Historical
Mina Kirstein was born in Boston, Massachusetts in 1896 and spent her childhood growing up in Rochester, New York, with her parents, Louis E Kirstein, a merchant, her mother Rose Stein and brothers Lincoln and George Kirstein. In 1912 the family returned to Boston where her father was the director of Filene's department store. Mina was educated at home and came to Smith College where in 1918 she received a B.A. In 1920 she was awarded the M.A. from Columbia University. She returned to Smith College to teach English and remained here until 1934. Between 1935 and 1938 she worked for the Mercury Theatre of the Air in New York City, with Orson Welles and John Houseman, as a researcher and promoter of the theatre. She continued to write throughout her career, publishing a book about her marriage and the early death of her husand Henry Tomlinson Curtiss in 1927 called The Midst of Life. She wrote several radio programs in the 1930s, translated Proust, and wrote a biography of Georges Bizet in the 1940s. A visit to Russia in 1962 resulted in a biography of the Russian ballerina Anna Ivanovna. In the 1970s she wrote Other People's Letters: A Memoir which chronicled her interest in Proust. She supplemented her craft of writing with book reviews and editorials for newspapers. She returned to teach at Smith College in the early 1940s, then again as a visiting lecturer, giving courses in the art of biography.
She was an Associate Professor of English at Smith between 1920-1934, left the College only to return to teach between 1940-1945. She was a Visiting Professor of English Language and Literature in 1976.
Mina Kirstein Curtiss was 89 years old when she died in Bridgeport, Connecticut on October 31, 1985 after a long illness.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain biographical information, correspondence, examinations, lectures, publications and student papers of Mina Kirstein Curtiss documenting her career as a professor of English at Smith College.
Related Material
Class of 1918 Records
Mina Kirstein Curtiss Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Smith College--Students.; Curtiss, Mina Kirstein, 1896-; Smith College--Faculty.; Chase, Mary Ellen, 1887-1973.; Comstock, Ada Louise.; Flanagan, Hallie, 1890-1969.; Ferber, Edna, 1887-1968.; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984.; Nicolson, Marjorie Hope, 1894-; West, Rebecca, Dame, 1892-
- Biographical Information (Box 736, Folder 1)
- Student Papers for English 11a class, 1922 May (Box 736, Folder 2-3)
- Faculty Appointment cards, 1920-1941 (Box 736, Folder 4)
- Lecture Notes for Biography Course, undated (Box 736, Folder 5)
- Undergraduate Essays, 1917; undated (Box 736, Folder 6-7)
- Undergraduate Examinations, undated (Box 736, Folder 8)
- Undergraduate Lecture Notes, undated (Box 736, Folder 9)
- Grades, 1915-1918 (Box 736, Folder 10)
- War Service, 1918-1919 (Box 736, Folder 11)
- Correspondence
  - Aaron, Daniel, 1943; 1971 (Box 737, Folder 12)
  - Alderman, Edwin A., 1928-1930 (Box 737, Folder 13)
  - Blount, Victoria, 1923 (Box 737, Folder 14)
  - Bradshaw, Margaret B., 1928 (Box 737, Folder 15)
  - Broad, Margaret, 1920 (Box 737, Folder 16)
  - Chase, Mary Ellen, 1940-1949 (Box 737, Folder 17)
  - Cheever, Louisa, 1928 (Box 737, Folder 18)
  - Churchill, Vieno (Kajander), 1941 (Box 737, Folder 19)
  - Comstock, Ada Louise, 1920; 1932 (Box 737, Folder 20)
  - Crouse, Dorothy B., 1922 (Box 737, Folder 21)
  - Davis, Hallie Flanagan, 1943 (Box 737, Folder 22)
  - Davis, Herbert J., 1940; 1944 (Box 737, Folder 23)
  - Dunn, Elizabeth Irwin, 1942 (Box 737, Folder 24)
  - Dunn, Esther Cloudman, 1931; 1940 (Box 737, Folder 25)
  - Dunn, Esther Cloudman, 1943; 1945 (Box 737, Folder 26)
  - Ferber, Edna, 1924 (Box 737, Folder 27)
  - Fisher, Alfred Y., 1943-1944 (Box 737, Folder 28)
  - Flanner, Janet, 1949 (Box 737, Folder 29)
  - Green, Shirley, 1941 (Box 737, Folder 30)
  - Harris, Rose Marie, 1933 (Box 737, Folder 31)
  - Heinlein, Virginia, 1918; undated (Box 737, Folder 32)
  - Hill, Charles J., undated (Box 737, Folder 33)
  - Hoyt, Helen, 1920 (Box 737, Folder 34)
  - Jordan, Mary Augusta, 1918-1930; 1933 (Box 737, Folder 35)
  - Kelly, Donald C., 1976 (Box 737, Folder 36)
  - Knopf, Alfred A., 1936 (Box 737, Folder 37)
  - Kuhn, Samuel L., 1918-1919 (Box 737, Folder 38)
  - Laurence, Hilda, 1945 (Box 737, Folder 39)
  - Lewis, Mary Delia, 1920 (Box 737, Folder 40)
  - Lewis, Nell Battle, 1918 (Box 737, Folder 41)
  - Lincoln, Eleanor T., 1945 (Box 737, Folder 42)
  - Lindgren, Ethel John, 1924; 1933 (Box 737, Folder 43)
  - Linley, Sarah Isabel, 1922-1923 (Box 737, Folder 44)
  - Luch, Emily Lenore, 1953 (Box 737, Folder 45)
  - McBride, Mary Margaret, undated (Box 737, Folder 46)
  - McEldowny, Genevieve, 192? (Box 737, Folder 47)
  - McLaughlin, Mignon, undated (Box 737, Folder 48)
  - Malone, Isabel (Gardner), 1945 (Box 737, Folder 49)
  - Mehrtens, Ruth Beatrice, 1941 (Box 737, Folder 50)
  - Mencken, Henry L., 1936 (Box 737, Folder 51)
  - Michael, Virginia Mae, 1942-1943 (Box 737, Folder 52)
  - Miller, Marcella, 1923-1924 (Box 737, Folder 53)
  - Neilson, Elizabeth (Muser), undated (Box 737, Folder 54)
  - Nicolson, Marjorie Hope, 1940 (Box 737, Folder 55)
  - Patch, Howard, 1942 (Box 737, Folder 56)
  - Potter, Olive Elizabeth, 1923 (Box 737, Folder 57)
  - Powell, Frances, undated (Box 737, Folder 58)
  - Rice, Richard Ashley, 1920-1923; 1928 (Box 737, Folder 59)
  - Riggs, Margaret Mary, 1941; 1944 (Box 737, Folder 60)
  - Rubins, Marian, 1920 (Box 737, Folder 61)
  - Russell, Doris Aurelia, 1933 (Box 737, Folder 62)
  - Smith, Elizabeth (Olmsted), 1935 (Box 737, Folder 63)
  - Spectorsky, Miriam Lenore, 1922-1923 (Box 737, Folder 64)
  - Stapleton, Katharine Laurence, 1933 (Box 737, Folder 65)
  - Tildsley, Kathleen, 1923 (Box 737, Folder 66)
  - West, Rebecca, 1978 (Box 737, Folder 67)
  - Whitman, Sarah, 1918 (Box 737, Folder 68)
  - Wilder, Charlotte Elizabeth, undated (Box 737, Folder 69)
  - Wright, Polly, 1928 (Box 737, Folder 70)
  - Yeadon, Henry, 1918 (Box 737, Folder 71)
  - Yoerg, Elizabeth Ann, 1941-1942 (Box 737, Folder 72)
- Publications
  - Bibliography (Box 738, Folder 73)
  - "Chosen," in Massachusetts Review, 1983 Summer (Box 738, Folder 74)
  - Letters Home, 1944 (Box 738, Folder 75)
  - The Midst of Life, 1933 (Box 738, Folder 76)
  - The Midst of Life, manuscript (Box 738.1)
  - Olive, Cypress and Palm, 1930 (Box 738, Folder 77)